Guide to the Harry B. Mitchell Papers 1953-1965
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Harry B. Mitchell papers
1953-1965
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Mitchell, Harry B. (Harry Browning), 1933-
2441
0.6 linear feet
The Harry B. Mitchell Papers consist of correspondence, brochures, pamphlets, newspaper articles, government documents, working papers, legislative lists, a photo story, a slide presentation and slide, various bill drafts, broadsides, state reports, congratulatory letter, and recommendations. The materials pertain to Mitchell service as co-chair of the Jaycees Legislative Committee in 1962, service chairing the Conservation Committee of the Jaycees, and his 1963 American Motors Non-Professional Conservation Award.
Harry B. Mitchell was a member of the Junior Chamber of Commerce (Jaycees) from Great Falls, Montana. In the fall of 1962, he became the co-chairman of the Legislative Committee for the Montana State Jaycees. He spent the next 2 years promoting the protection of the natural waterways of Montana, especially fishing habitat, from damage by road construction and hydraulic activities. The Jaycees created a Conservation Committee in 1963 and Mitchell served as its chair. He was honored for his work with a 1963 American Motors Company Non-professional Conservation Award.
The Mitchell papers have been divided into three series. Series one contains materials created or collected by Mitchell while serving as co-chair of the Jaycees Legislative Committee in 1962. Mitchell's work on the committee related to the development of Substitute Senate Bill 45, passed on March 11, 1963, a state bill protecting fishing waters from highway construction. Papers include correspondence, brochures, pamphlets, newspaper articles, government documents, working papers, legislative lists, a photo story showing results of stream bed alterations, a slide presentation and slides promoting the bill, draft bills and the final version of the bill. Series two contains materials created or collected by Mitchell while serving as the chair of the Conservation Committee of the Jaycees. These papers relate to the committee's efforts to introduce a similar Federal bill to protect fishing waters. Papers include correspondence, newspaper articles, broadsides, state reports and official interdepartmental correspondence between Federal departments involved. These papers relate to the Jaycees continuing advocacy of the Stream Preservation Act of 1963 (SSB #45), Clean Water campaign, and the controversies over Federal construction plans for Interstate Highway I-15 along the Missouri River near Wolf Point, Montana. Series three contains the program, congratulatory letters, recommendations, newspaper clippings, and correspondence related to the awarding of a 1963 American Motors Non-Professional Conservation Award to Harry B. Mitchell.
Series 1 Montana Junior Chamber of Commerce Legislative Committee, 1953-1963
Series 2 Montana Junior Chamber of Commerce Conservation Committee, 1963-1964
Series 3 American Motors Conservation Award, 1963
This collection is open for research.
The Harry B. Mitchell papers were donated to Special Collections on April 29, 2002 by Tom Palmer of the Information Department of the Montana Fish, Wildlife and Parks Department.
American Motors Corporation; Montana Junior Chamber of Commerce-Conservation Committee; Montana Junior Chamber of Commerce-Legislative Committee
Montana--Environmental Conditions; Montana--Politics and government--20th century; Montana--Politics and government; Montana
Fishes--Conservation--Montana; Roads--Design and construction--Environmental aspects--Montana; Stream conservation--Montana; Water quality-Montana; Conservationists--Montana
Civic Activism; Environmental Conditions; Fishing and Canning; Water and Water Rights; Montana; Photographs
Photographs; Photographs
- Montana Junior Chamber of Commerce Legislative Committee, 1953-1963; Series 1
  Papers created or collected by Harry Mitchell in his work as co-chair of the Jaycees Legislative Committee, especially pertaining to the campaign for Senate Substitute Bill #45. Materials that predate Mitchell's term on the committee represent research on the issue that he gathered.
  - Originals or photocopies of correspondence, 1962 April 2 - 1963 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, transcripts of radio broadcasts and editorials (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Plans and time-line of campaign (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Slide show outline and slides (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Perry Nelson photo book (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets, reports, journal articles (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Water court and legislative papers: hearings, directories, roll call, draft bills, vote summary, and final bill (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Montana Junior Chamber of Commerce Conservation Committee, 1963-1964; Series 2
  Papers created or collected by Mitchell as chair of the Jaycees Conservation Committee, especially in advocating federal legislation to protect fishing waters during the construction of interstate highways.
  - Originals or photocopies of correspondence, 1963 June 7 - 1963 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Originals or photocopies of correspondence, 1964 January 23, - 1964 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conservation Committee stream preservation papers (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Papers and correspondence: campaign for Federal legislation (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Additional Jaycee Conservation Committee project papers, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - I-15 on Missouri River road controversy (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - I-15 on Missouri River road controversy (cont.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Report on Supplemental Location Study in Gary Cooper Ranch Vicinity," State of Montana Highway Department, 1964 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- American Motors Conservation Award, 1963; Series 3
  Papers, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia for the 1963 American Motors conservation Award.
  - American Motors Conservation Award binder (Box 2, Folder 4)